١ ألف لام را
1. Alif-Lam-Ra.
تلك آيات الكتاب المبين
These are the verses of the clear Book.
٢ إنا أنزلناه قرآنا عربيا لعلكم تعقلون
2. Indeed, We have sent it down as an Arabic Quran
so that you may understand.
٣ نحن نقص عليك أحسن القصص بما أوحينا إليك هذا القرآن
3. We relate to you ˹O Prophet˺ the best of stories
through Our revelation of this Quran,
وإن كنت من قبله لمن الغافلين
though before this you were totally unaware ˹of
them˺.
٤ إذ قال يوسف لأبيه يا أبت إني رأيت أحد عشر كوكبا
4. ˹Remember˺ when Joseph said to his father, "O my
dear father! Indeed I dreamt of eleven stars,
والشمس والقمر رأيتهم لي ساجدين
and the sun, and the moon—I saw them prostrating to
me!"
٥ قال يا بني لا تقصص رؤياك على إخوتك فيكيدوا لك كيدا
5. He replied, "O my dear son! Do not relate your
vision to your brothers, or they will devise a plot
against you.
إن الشيطان للإنسان عدو مبين
Surely Satan is a sworn enemy to humankind.
٦ وكذلك يجتبيك ربك ويعلمك من تأويل الأحاديث
6. And so will your Lord choose you ˹O Joseph˺, and
teach you the interpretation of dreams,
ويتم نعمته عليك وعلى آل يعقوب كما أتمها على أبويك من قبل
and perfect His favour upon you and the descendants
of Jacob—˹just˺ as He once perfected it upon your
forefathers,
كما أتمها على أبويك من قبل إبراهيم وإسحاق
of Jacob—˹just˺ as He once perfected it upon your
forefathers, Abraham and Isaac.
إن ربك عليم حكيم
Surely your Lord is All-Knowing, All-Wise."
٧ لقد كان في يوسف وإخوته آيات للسائلين
7. Indeed, in the story of Joseph and his brothers
there are lessons for all who ask.
٨ إذ قالوا ليوسف وأخوه أحب إلى أبينا منا ونحن عصبة
8. ˹Remember˺ when they said ˹to one another˺,
"Surely Joseph and his brother ˹Benjamin˺ are more
beloved to our father than we, even though we are a
group of so many.
إن أبانا لفي ضلال مبين
Indeed, our father is clearly mistaken.
٩ أقتلوا يوسف أو اطرحوه أرضا يخل لكم وجه أبيكم
9. Kill Joseph or cast him out to some ˹distant˺
land so that our father's attention will be only
ours,
وتكونوا من بعده قوما صالحين
then after that you may ˹repent and˺ become
righteous people!"
١٠ قال قائل منهم لا تقتلوا يوسف وألقوه في غيابة الجب
10. One of them said, "Do not kill Joseph. But if
you must do something, throw him into the bottom of
a well
يلتقطه بعض السيارة إن كنتم فاعلين
so perhaps he may be picked up by some travellers."
١١ قالوا يا أبانا ما لك لا تأمنا على يوسف وإنا له لناصحون
11. They said, "O our father! Why do you not trust
us with Joseph, although we truly wish him well?
١٢ أرسله معنا غدا يرتع ويلعب وإنا له لحافظون
12. Send him out with us tomorrow so that he may
enjoy himself and play. And we will really watch
over him."
١٣ قال إني ليحزنني أن تذهبوا به وأخاف أن يأكله الذئب وأنتم عنه غافلون
13. He responded, "It would truly sadden me if you
took him away with you, and I fear that a wolf may
devour him while you are negligent of him."
١٤ قالوا لئن أكله الذئب ونحن عصبة إنا إذا لخاسرون
14. They said, "If a wolf were to devour him,
despite our strong group, then we would certainly be
losers!"
١٥ فلما ذهبوا به وأجمعوا أن يجعلوه في غيابة الجب
15. And so, when they took him away and decided to
throw him into the bottom of the well,
وأوحينا إليه لتنبئنهم بأمرهم هذا وهم لا يشعرون
We inspired him: "˹One day˺ you will remind them of
this deed of theirs while they are unaware ˹of who
you are˺."
١٦ وجاءوا أباهم عشاء يبكون
16. Then they returned to their father in the
evening, weeping.
١٧ قالوا يا أبانا إنا ذهبنا نستبق وتركنا يوسف عند متاعنا فأكله الذئب
17. They cried, "Our father! We went racing and left
Joseph with our belongings, and a wolf devoured him!
وما أنت بمؤمن لنا ولو كنا صادقين
But you will not believe us, no matter how truthful
we are."
١٨ وجاءوا على طميصه بدم كذب قال بل سولتنكم أنفسكم أمرا فصبر جميل
18. And they brought his shirt, stained with false
blood. He responded, "No! Your souls must have
tempted you to do something ˹evil˺. So ˹I can only
endure with˺ beautiful patience!
والله المستعان على ما تصفون
It is Allah's help that I seek to bear your claims."
١٩ وجاءت سيارة فأرسلوا واردهم فأدلى دلوه قال يا بشرى هذا غلام
19. And there came some travellers, and they sent
their water-boy who let down his bucket into the
well. He cried out, "Oh, what a great find! Here is
a boy!"
وأسروه بضاعة والله عليم بما يعملون
And they took him secretly ˹to be sold˺ as
merchandise, but Allah is All-Knowing of what they
did.
٢٠ وشروه بثمن بخص دراهم معدودة وكانوا فيه من الزاهدين
20. They ˹later˺ sold him for a cheap price, just a
few silver coins—only wanting to get rid of him.
٢١ وقال الذي اشتراه من مصر لمرأته أكرمي مثواه عسى أن ينفعنا أو نتخذه ولدا
21. The man from Egypt who bought him said to his
wife, "Take good care of him, perhaps he may be
useful to us or we may adopt him as a son."
وكذلك مكنا ليوسف في الأرض ولنعلمه من تأويل الأحاديث
This is how We established Joseph in the land, so
that We might teach him the interpretation of
dreams.
والله غالب على أمره ولكن أكثر الناس لا يعلمون
Allah's Will always prevails, but most people do not
know.
٢٢ ولما بلغ أشده آتيناه حكما وعلما وكذلك نجزي المحسنين
22. And when he reached maturity, We gave him wisdom
and knowledge. This is how We reward the good-doers.
٢٣ وراودته التي هو في بيتها عن نفسه وغلقت الأبواب وقالت هيت لك
23. And the lady, in whose house he lived, tried to
seduce him. She locked the doors ˹firmly˺ and said,
"Come to me!" He replied, "Allah is my refuge!
قال معاذ الله إنه ربي أحسن مثوايا إنه لا يفلح الظالمون
It is ˹not right to betray˺ my master, who has taken
good care of me. Indeed, the wrongdoers never
succeed."
٢٤ ولقد همت به وهم بها لولا أرآ برهان ربه كذلك لنصرف عنه السوء والفحشاء إنه من عبادنا المخلصين
24. She advanced towards him, and he would have done
likewise, had he not seen a sign from his Lord. This
is how We kept evil and indecency away from him, for
he was truly one of Our chosen servants.
٢٥ واستبق الباب وقدت قميصه من دبر وألف يا سيدها لدى الباب
25. They raced for the door and she tore his shirt
from the back, only to find her husband at the door.
قالت ما جزاء من أراد بأهلك سوءا إلا أن يسجن أو عذاب أليم
She cried, "What is the penalty for someone who
tried to violate your wife, except imprisonment or a
painful punishment?"
٢٦ قال هي راودتني عن نفسي وشهد شاهد من أهلها إن كان قميصه قد من قبل فصدقت وهو من الكاذبين
26. Joseph responded, "It was she who tried to
seduce me." And a witness from her own family
testified: "If his shirt is torn from the front,
then she has told the truth and he is a liar.
٢٧ وإن كان قميصه قد من دبر فكذبت وهو من الصادقين
27. But if it is torn from the back, then she has
lied and he is truthful."
٢٨ فلما رأى قميصه قد من دبر قال إنه من كيدكن عظيم
28. So when her husband saw that Joseph's shirt was
torn from the back, he said ˹to her˺, "This must be
˹an example˺ of the cunning of you ˹women˺! Indeed,
your cunning is so shrewd!
٢٩ يوسف أعرض عن هذا واستغفرين ذنبك إنك كنت من الخاطئين
29. O Joseph! Forget about this. And you ˹O wife˺!
Seek forgiveness for your sin. It certainly has been
your fault."
٣٠ وقال نسوة في المدينة امرأة العزيز تراود فتاها عن نفسه قد شغفها حبا
30. Some women of the city gossiped, "The Chief
Minister's wife is trying to seduce her slave-boy.
Love for him has plagued her heart.
إنا لنراها في ضلال مبين
Some women of the city gossiped, "The Chief
Minister's wife is trying to seduce her slave-boy.
Love for him has plagued her heart. Indeed, we see
that she is clearly mistaken."
٣١ فلما سمعت بمكرهن أرسلت إليهن وأعتدت لهن متكأا وآتت كل واحدة منهن سكينا وقالت خرج عليهم
31. When she heard about their gossip, she invited
them and set a banquet for them. She gave each one a
knife, then said to Joseph, "Come out before them."
When they saw him,
فلما رأينه أكبرنه وقطعن أيديهن وقلن حاش لله ما هذا بشرا إن هذا إلا ملك كريم
they were so stunned ˹by his beauty˺ that they cut
their hands, and exclaimed, "Good God! This cannot
be human; this must be a noble angel!"
٣٢ قالت فذلكن الذي لمتنني فيه ولقد راوته عن نفسه فاستعصم
32. She said, "This is the one for whose love you
criticized me! I did try to seduce him but he
˹firmly˺ refused.
ولئن لم يفعل ما آمره ليسجنن وليكون من الصاغرين
And if he does not do what I order him to, he will
certainly be imprisoned and ˹fully˺ disgraced."
٣٣ قال رب السجن أحب إلي مما يدعونني إليه وإلا تصرف عني كيدهن أصب إليهن وأكون من الجاهلين
33. He said, "My Lord, prison is more to my liking
than that to which they invite me. And if You do not
avert from me their plan, I might incline toward
them and ˹thus˺ be of the ignorant."
٣٤ فاستجاب له ربه فصرف عنه كيدهن إنه هو السميع العليم
34. So his Lord responded to him, turning their
cunning away from him. Surely He is the All-Hearing,
All-Knowing.
٣٥ ثم بدى لهم من بعد ما رأوا الآيات ليسجننه حتى حين
35. And so it occurred to those in charge, despite
seeing all the proofs ˹of his innocence˺, that he
should be imprisoned for a while.
٣٦ ودخل معه السجن فتيان قال أحدهما إني أراني أعصر خمرا
36. And two other servants went to jail with Joseph.
One of them said, "I dreamt I was pressing wine."
The other said,
وقال الآخر إني أراني أحمل فوق رأسي خبزا تأكل الطير منه
"I dreamt I was carrying ˹some˺ bread on my head,
from which birds were eating." ˹Then both said,˺
"Tell us their interpretation,
نبئنا بتأويله إنا نراك من المحسنين
for we surely see you as one of the good-doers."
٣٧ قال لا يأتيكما طعام ترزقانه إلا نبأتكما بتأويله قبل أن يأتيكما ذلكما مما علمني ربي
37. Joseph replied, "I can even tell you what kind
of meal you will be served before you receive it.
This ˹knowledge˺ is from what my Lord has taught me.
إني تركت ملة قوم لا يؤمنون بالله وهم بالآخرة هم كافرون
I have shunned the faith of a people who disbelieve
in Allah and deny the Hereafter.
٣٨ واتبعت ملة آبائي إبراهيم وإسحاق ويعقوب
38. I follow the faith of my fathers: Abraham,
Isaac,
ما كان لنا أن نشرك بالله من شيء ذلك من فضل الله علينا وعلى الناس
and Jacob. It is not ˹right˺ for us to associate
anything with Allah ˹in worship˺. This is part of
Allah's grace upon us and humanity,
ولكن أكثر الناس لا يشترون
but most people are not grateful.
٣٩ يا صاحبي السجن أأرباب متفرقون خير أم الله الواحد القهار
39. O my fellow-prisoners! Which is far better: many
different lords or Allah—the One, the Supreme?
٤٠ ما تعبدون من دونه إلا أسماء سميتموها أنتم وآباؤكم ما أنزل الله بها من سلطان
40. Whatever ˹idols˺ you worship instead of Him are
mere names which you and your forefathers have made
up—a practice Allah has never authorized.
إن الحكم إلا لله أمر أن لا تعبدوا إلا إياه ذلك الدين القيم ولكن أكثر الناس لا يعلمون
It is only Allah Who decides. He has commanded that
you worship none but Him. That is the upright faith,
but most people do not know.
٤١ يا صاحبي السجن أما أحدكما فيسقي ربه خمرا
41. "O my fellow-prisoners! ˹The first˺ one of you
will serve wine to his master,
وأما الآخر فيسلب فتأكل الطير من رأسه قضي الأمر الذي فيه تستفتيان
and the other will be crucified and the birds will
eat from his head. The matter about which you
inquired has been decided."
٤٢ وقال للذي ظن أنه ناج منهم اذكرني عند ربك فأنساه الشيطان ذكر ربه فلبث في السجن بطع سنين
42. Then he said to the one he knew would survive,
"Mention me in the presence of your master." But
Satan made him forget to mention Joseph to his
master, so he remained in prison for several years.
٤٣ وقال الملك إني أرى سبع بقرات سمان يأكلهن سبع عجاف
43. And ˹one day˺ the King said, "I dreamt of seven
fat cows eaten up by seven skinny ones;
وسبع سنبلات خضر وأخر يابسات
and seven green ears of grain and ˹seven˺ others
dry.
يا أيها الملأ أفتوني في رؤياي إن كنتم للرؤيا تعبرون
O chiefs! Tell me the meaning of my dream if you can
interpret dreams."
٤٤ قالوا أضغاث أحلام وما نحن بتأويل الأحلام بعالمين
44. They replied, "These are confused visions and we
do not know the interpretation of such dreams."
٤٥ وقال الذين جاء منهما وادكر بعد أمة أنا أنبئكم بتأويله فأرسنون
45. ˹Finally,˺ the surviving ex-prisoner remembered
˹Joseph˺ after a long time and said, "I will tell
you its interpretation, so send me forth ˹to
Joseph˺."
٤٦ يوسف أيها الصديق أفتنا في سبع بقرات سمان يأكلهن سبع عجاف
46. ˹He said,˺ "Joseph, O man of truth! Interpret
for us ˹the dream of˺ seven fat cows eaten up by
seven skinny ones;
وسبع سنبلات خضر وأخر يابسات لعلي أرجع إلى الناس لعلهم يعلمون
and seven green ears of grain and ˹seven˺ others
dry, so that I may return to the people and let them
know."
٤٧ قال تزرعون سبع سنين دأبا فما حصدتم فذروه في سنبله إلا قليلا مما تأكلون
47. Joseph replied, "You will plant ˹grain˺ for
seven consecutive years, leaving in the ear whatever
you will harvest, except for the little you will
eat.
٤٨ ثم يأتي من بعد ذلك سبع شداد يأكل ما قدمتم لهن إلا قليلا مما تحصنون
48. Then after that will come seven years of great
hardship which will consume whatever you have saved,
except the little you will store ˹for seed˺.
٤٩ ثم يأتي من بعد ذلك عام فيه يغاث الناس وفيه يعصرون
49. Then after that will come a year in which people
will receive abundant rain and they will press ˹oil
and wine˺."
٥٠ وقال الملك أتوني به فلما جاءه الرسول قال ارجع إلى ربك فاسألهما بال النسوة التي قطعن أيديهن
50. The King ˹then˺ said, "Bring him to me." When
the messenger came to him, Joseph said, "Go back to
your master and ask him about the case of the women
who cut their hands.
إن ربي بكيدهن عليم
Surely my Lord has ˹full˺ knowledge of their
cunning."
٥١ قال ما خطبكن إذ راودتن يوسف عن نفسه قلن حاش لله ما علمنا عليه من سوء
51. The King asked ˹the women˺, "What did you get
when you tried to seduce Joseph?" They replied,
"Allah forbid! We know nothing indecent about him."
Then the Chief Minister's wife admitted,
قالت امرأة العزيز الآن حصحص الحق أنا راودته عن نفسه وإنه لمن الصادقين
"Now the truth has come to light. It was I who tried
to seduce him, and he is surely truthful.
٥٢ ذلك ليعلم أني لم أخنه بالغيب وأن الله لا يهدي كيد الخائنين
52. From this, Joseph should know that I did not
speak dishonestly about him in his absence, for
Allah certainly does not guide the scheming of the
dishonest.
٥٣ وما أبرئ نفسي إن النفس لأمارة بالسوء إلا ما رحم ربي إن ربي غفور رحيم
53. And I do not seek to free myself from blame, for
indeed the soul is ever inclined to evil, except
those shown mercy by my Lord. Surely my Lord is All-
Forgiving, Most Merciful."
٥٤ وقال الملك أتوني به أستخلصه لنفسي فلما كلمه قال إنك اليوم لدينا مكين أمين
54. The King said, "Bring him to me. I will employ
him exclusively in my service." And when Joseph
spoke to him, the King said, "Today you are highly
esteemed and fully trusted by us."
٥٥ قال جعلني على خزائن الأرض إني حفيظ عليم
55. Joseph proposed, "Put me in charge of the store-
houses of the land, for I am truly reliable and
adept."
٥٦ وكذلك مكنا ليوسف في الأرض يتبوأ منها حيث يشاء
56. This is how We established Joseph in the land to
settle wherever he pleased.
نصيب برحمتنا من نشاء
We shower Our mercy on whoever We will,
ولا نضيع أجر المحسنين
and We never discount the reward of the good-doers.
٥٧ ولأجر الآخرة خير للذين آمنوا وكانوا يتقون
57. And the reward of the Hereafter is far better
for those who are faithful and are mindful ˹of
Allah˺.
٥٨ وجاء إخوة يوسف فدخلوا عليه فعرفهم وهم له منكرون
58. And Joseph's brothers came and entered his
presence. He recognized them but they were unaware
of who he really was.
٥٩ ولما جهزهم بجهازهم قال أتوني بأخ لكم من أبيكم
59. When he had provided them with their supplies,
he demanded, "Bring me your brother on your father's
side.
ألا ترون أني أوف الكيل وأنا خير المنزنين
Do you not see that I give full measure and I am the
best of hosts?
٦٠ فإن لم تأتوني به فلا كيل لكم عندي ولا تقربون
60. But if you do not bring him to me ˹next time˺, I
will have no grain for you, nor will you ever come
close to me again."
٦١ قالوا سنراود عنه أباه وإنا لفاعلون
61. They promised, "We will try to convince his
father to let him come. We will certainly do ˹our
best˺."
٦٢ وقال لفتيانه اجعلوا بضاعتهم في رحالهم لعلهم يعرفونها
62. Joseph ordered his servants to put his brothers'
money back into their saddlebags so that they would
إذا انقلبوا إلى أهلهم لعلهم يرجعون
find it when they returned to their family and
perhaps they would come back.
٦٣ فلما رجعوا إلى أبيهم قالوا يا أبانا منع منا الكيل
63. When Joseph's brothers returned to their father,
they pleaded, "O our father! We have been denied
˹further˺ supplies. So send our brother with us so
that we may receive our measure,
فأرسل معنا أخانا نكتل وإنا له لحافظون
and we will definitely watch over him."
٦٤ قال هل آمنكم عليه إلا كما أمنتكم على أخيه من قبل
64. He responded, "Should I trust you with him as I
once trusted you with his brother ˹Joseph˺? But
˹only˺ Allah is the best Protector,
فالله خير حافظا وهو أرحم الراحمين
and He is the Most Merciful of the merciful."
٦٥ ولما فتحوا متاعهم وجدوا بضاعتهم ردت إليهم
65. When they opened their bags, they discovered
that their money had been returned to them.
قالوا يا أبانا ما نبغي هذه بضاعتنا ردت إلينا
They argued, "O our father! What more can we ask
for? Here is our money, fully returned to us. Now we
can buy more food for our family.
ونمير أهلنا ونحفظ أخانا ونزداد كيل بعير
We will watch over our brother, and obtain an extra
camel-load of grain. That load can be easily
secured."
ذلك كيل يسير
When they opened their bags, they discovered that
their money had been returned to them. They argued,
"O our father! What more can we ask for? Here is our
money, fully returned to us. Now we can buy more
food for our family. We will watch over our brother,
and obtain an extra camel-load of grain. That load
can be easily secured."
٦٦ قال لن أرسله معكم حتى تؤتون موثقا من الله
66. Jacob insisted, "I will not send him with you
until you give me a solemn oath by Allah that you
will certainly bring him back to me, unless you are
totally overpowered." Then after they had given him
their oaths, he concluded, "Allah
لتأتنني به إلا أن يحاط بكم
is
فلما آتوه موثقهم قال الله على ما نقول وكيل
a Witness to what we have said."
٦٧ وقال يا بني لا تدخلوا من باب واحد
67. He then instructed ˹them˺, "O my sons! Do not
enter ˹the city˺ all through one gate,
وادخلوا من أبواب متفرقة
but through separate gates.
وما أغني عنكم من الله من شيء
I cannot help you against ˹what is destined by˺
Allah in the least.
إن الحكم إلا لله عليه توكلت وعليه فليتوكل المتوكلون
It is only Allah Who decides. In Him I put my trust.
And in Him let the faithful put their trust."
٦٨ ولما دخلوا من حيث أمرهم أبوهم ما كان يغني عنهم من الله من شيء
68. Then when they entered as their father had
instructed them, this did not help them against ˹the
Will of˺ Allah whatsoever.
إلا حاجة في نفس يعقوب قضاها
It was just a desire in Jacob's heart which he
satisfied.
وإنه لذو علم لما علمناه ولكن أكثر الناس لا يعلمون
He was truly blessed with ˹great˺ knowledge because
of what We had taught him, but most people have no
knowledge.
٦٩ ولما دخلوا على يوسف آوى إليه أخاه
69. When they entered Joseph's presence, he called
his brother ˹Benjamin˺ aside, and confided ˹to him˺,
"I am indeed your brother ˹Joseph˺!
قال إني أنا أخوك فلا تبتئس بما كانوا يعملون
So do not feel distressed about what they have been
doing."
٧٠ فلما جهزهم بجهازهم جعل السقاية في رحل أخيه
70. When Joseph had provided them with supplies, he
slipped the royal cup into his brother's bag.
ثم أذن مؤذن أيتها العير إنكم لسارقون
Then a herald cried, "O people of the caravan! You
must be thieves!"
٧١ قالوا وأقبلوا عليهم ماذا تفقدون
71. They asked, turning back, "What have you lost?"
٧٢ قالوا نفقد صواع الملك ولمن جاء به حمل بعير وأنا به زعيم
72. The herald ˹along with the guards˺ replied, "We
have lost the King's measuring cup. And whoever
brings it will be awarded a camel-load ˹of grain˺. I
guarantee it."
٧٣ قالوا تالله لقد علمتم ما جئنا لنفسد في الأرض وما كنا سارقين
73. Joseph's brothers replied, "By Allah! You know
well that we did not come to cause trouble in the
land, nor are we thieves."
٧٤ قالوا فما جزاؤه إن كنتم كاذبين
74. Joseph's men asked, "What should be the price
for theft, if you are lying?"
٧٥ قالوا جزاؤه من وجد في رحله فهو جزاؤه كذلك نجزي الظالمين
75. Joseph's brothers responded, "The price will be
˹the enslavement of˺ the one in whose bag the cup is
found. That is how we punish the wrongdoers."
٧٦ فبدأ بأوعيتهم قبل وعاء أخيه ثم استخرجها من وعاء
76. Joseph began searching their bags before that of
his brother ˹Benjamin˺, then brought it out of
Benjamin's bag.
أخيه كذلك كدنا ليوسف ما كان ليأخذ أخاه في دين الملك
This is how We inspired Joseph to plan. He could not
have taken his brother under the King's law,
إلا أن يشاء الله نرفع درجات من نشاء
but Allah had so willed. We elevate in rank whoever
We will.
وفوق كل ذي علم عليم
But above those ranking in knowledge is the One All-
Knowing.
٧٧ قالوا إن يسرق فقد سرق أخ له من قبل فأسرها يوسف في نفسه ولم يبدها لهم
77. ˹To distance themselves,˺ Joseph's brothers
argued, "If he has stolen, so did his ˹full˺ brother
before." But Joseph suppressed his outrage—revealing
nothing to them—and said ˹to himself˺,
قال أنتم شر مكانا والله أعلم بما تصفون
"You are in such an evil position, and Allah knows
best ˹the truth of˺ what you claim."
٧٨ قالوا يا أيها العزيز إن له أبا شيخا كبيرا فخذ أحدنا مكانه إنا نراك من المحسنين
78. They appealed, "O Chief Minister! He has a very
old father, so take one of us instead. We surely see
you as one of the good-doers."
٧٩ قال معاذ الله أن نأخذ إلا من وجدنا متاعنا عنده إنا إذا لظالمون
79. Joseph responded, "Allah forbid that we should
take other than the one with whom we found our
property. Otherwise, we would surely be unjust."
٨٠ فلما استيئسوا منه خلصوا نجيا
80. When they lost all hope in him, they spoke
privately.
قال كبيرهم ألم تعلموا أن أباكم قد أخذ عليكم موثقا من الله
The eldest of them said, "Do you not know that your
father had taken a solemn oath by Allah from you,
nor how you failed him regarding Joseph before? So I
am not leaving this land until my father allows me
to, or Allah decides for me.
ومن قبل ما فردتم في يوسف فلن أبرح الأرض حتى يأذن لي أبي أو يحكم الله لي وهو خير الحاكمين
For He is the Best of Judges.
٨١ ارجعوا إلى أبيكم فقولوا يا أبانا إن ابنك سرق وما شهدنا إلا بما علمنا وما كنا للغيب حافظين
81. Return to your father and say, 'O our father!
Your son committed theft. We testify only to what we
know. We could not guard against the unforeseen.
٨٢ واسأل القرية التي كنا فيها والعير التي أقبلنا فيها وإنا لصادقون
82. Ask ˹the people of˺ the land where we were and
the caravan we travelled with. We are certainly
telling the truth.'"
٨٣ قال بل سولت لكم أنفسكم أمرا فصبر جميل
83. He cried, "No! Your souls must have tempted you
to do something ˹evil˺. So ˹I am left with nothing
but˺ beautiful patience!
عسى الله أن يأتيني بهم جميعا إنه هو العليم الحكيم
I trust Allah will return them all to me. Surely He
˹alone˺ is the All-Knowing, All-Wise."
٨٤ وتولى عنهم وقال يا أسفى على يوسف وبيضت عيناه من الحزن فهو كظيم
84. He turned away from them, lamenting, "Alas, poor
Joseph!" And his eyes turned white out of the grief
he suppressed.
٨٥ قالوا تالله تفتأ تذكر يوسف حتى تكون حرضا أو تكون من الهالكين
85. They said, "By Allah! You will not cease to
remember Joseph until you lose your health or ˹even˺
your life."
٨٦ قال إنما أشكوا بثي وحزني إلى الله وأعلم من الله ما لا تعلمون
86. He replied, "I complain of my anguish and sorrow
only to Allah, and I know from Allah what you do not
know.
٨٧ يا بني يذهبوا فتحسسوا من يوسف وأخيه ولا تيأسوا من روح الله
87. O my sons! Go and search ˹diligently˺ for Joseph
and his brother. And do not lose hope in the mercy
of Allah,
إنه لا ييأس من روح الله إلا القوم الكافرون
for no one loses hope in Allah's mercy except those
with no faith."
٨٨ فلما دخلوا عليه قالوا يا أيها العزيز مسلا وأهلنا الضر وجئنا ببضاعة مزجات
88. When they entered Joseph's presence, they
pleaded, "O Chief Minister! We and our family have
been touched with hardship, and we have brought only
a few worthless coins,
فأوفلنا الكيل وتصدق علينا إن الله يجزي المتصدقين
but ˹please˺ give us our supplies in full and be
charitable to us. Indeed, Allah rewards the
charitable."
٨٩ قال هل علمتم ما فعلتم بيوسف وأخيه إذ أنتم جاهلون
89. He asked, "Do you remember what you did to
Joseph and his brother in your ignorance?"
٩٠ قالوا أئنك لأنت يوسف قال أنا يوسف وهذا أخي قد من الله علينا
90. They replied ˹in shock˺, "Are you really
Joseph?" He said, "I am Joseph, and here is my
brother ˹Benjamin˺! Allah has truly been gracious to
us.
إنه من يتق ويصبر فإن الله لا يضيع عجر المحسنين
Surely whoever is mindful ˹of Allah˺ and patient,
then certainly Allah never discounts the reward of
the good-doers."
٩١ قالوا تالله لقد آثرك الله علينا وإن كنا لخاطئين
91. They admitted, "By Allah! Allah has truly
preferred you over us, and we have surely been
sinful."
٩٢ قال لا تثريب عليكم اليوم يغفر الله لكم وهو أرحم الراحمين
92. Joseph said, "There is no blame on you today.
May Allah forgive you! He is the Most Merciful of
the merciful!
٩٣ اذهبوا بقميصي هذا فألقوه على وجه أبي يأتي بصيرا
93. Go with this shirt of mine and cast it over my
father's face, and he will regain his sight.
يأتي بصيرا وأتوني بأهلكم أجمعين
Then come back to me with your whole family."
٩٤ ولما فصلت العير قال أبوهم إني لأجد ريح يوسف لولا أن تفندون
94. When the caravan departed ˹from Egypt˺, their
father said ˹to those around him˺, "You may think I
am senile, but I certainly sense the smell of
Joseph."
٩٥ قالوا تالله إنك لفي طلالك القديم
95. They replied, "By Allah! You are definitely
still in your old delusion."
٩٦ فلما أن جاء البشير ألقاه على وجهه فارتد بصيرا
96. But when the bearer of the good news arrived, he
cast the shirt over Jacob's face, so he regained his
sight.
قال ألم أقل لكم إني أعلم من الله ما لا تعلمون
Jacob then said ˹to his children˺, "Did I not tell
you that I truly know from Allah what you do not
know?"
٩٧ قالوا يا أبان استغفر لنا ذنوبنا إنا كنا خاطئين
97. They begged, "O our father! Pray for the
forgiveness of our sins. We have certainly been
sinful."
٩٨ قال سوف أستغفر لكم ربي إنه هو الغفور الرحيم
98. He said, "I will pray to my Lord for your
forgiveness. He ˹alone˺ is indeed the All-Forgiving,
Most Merciful."
٩٩ فلما دخلوا على يوسف آوى إليه أبويه وقال دخلوا مصر إن شاء الله آمنين
99. When they entered Joseph's presence, he received
his parents ˹graciously˺ and said, "Enter Egypt,
Allah willing, in security."
١٠٠ ورفع أبويه على العرش وخروا له سجدا
100. Then he raised his parents to the throne, and
they all fell down in prostration to Joseph,
وقال يا أبت هذا تأويل رؤياي من قبل قد جعلها ربي حقا
who then said, "O my dear father! This is the
interpretation of my old dream. My Lord has made it
come true.
وقد أحسن بي إذ أخرجني من السجن وجاء بكم من البدو من بعد أن نزغ الشيطان
He was truly kind to me when He freed me from
prison, and brought you all from the desert after
Satan had ignited rivalry between me and my
siblings.
من بعد أن نزغ الشيطان بيني وبين إخوتي إن ربي لطيف لما يشاء إنه هو العليم الحكيم
and brought you all from the desert after Satan had
ignited rivalry between me and my siblings. Indeed
my Lord is subtle in fulfilling what He wills.
Surely He ˹alone˺ is the All-Knowing, All-Wise."
١٠١ ربي قد آتيتني من الملك وعلمتني من تأويل الأحاديث
101. "My Lord! You have surely granted me authority
and taught me the interpretation of dreams. ˹O˺
Originator of the heavens and the earth!
فاطر السماوات والأرض أنت ولي في الدنيا والآخرة
You are my Guardian in this world and the Hereafter.
أنت ولي في الدنيا والآخرة
توفني مسلما وألحقني بالصالحين
Allow me to die as one who submits and join me with
the righteous."
١٠٢ ذلك من أنباء الغيب نوحيه إليك
102. That is from the stories of the unseen which We
reveal to you ˹O Prophet˺.
وما كنت لديهم إذ أجمعوا أمرهم وهم يمكرون
You were not present when they ˹all˺ made up their
minds, and when they plotted ˹against Joseph˺.
١٠٣ وما أكثر الناس ولو حرصت بمؤمنين
103. And most people will not believe—no matter how
keen you are—
١٠٤ وما تسألهم عليه من أجر إنه إلا ذكر للعالمين
104. even though you are not asking them for a
reward for this ˹Quran˺. It is only a reminder to
the whole world.
١٠٥ وكأي من آية في السماوات والأرض يمرون عليها وهم عنها معرضون
105. How many signs in the heavens and the earth do
they pass by with indifference!
١٠٦ وما يؤمن أكثرهم بالله إلا وهم مشركون
106. And most of them do not believe in Allah
without associating others with Him ˹in worship˺.
١٠٧ أفأمنوا أن تأتيهم راشية من عذاب الله
107. Do they feel secure that an overwhelming
torment from Allah will not overtake them,
أو تأتيهم الساعة بغتة وهم لا يشعرون
or that the Hour will not take them by surprise when
they least expect ˹it˺?
١٠٨ قل هذه سبيلي أدعو إلى الله على بصيرة أنا ومن اتبعني
108. Say, ˹O Prophet,˺ "This is my way. I invite to
Allah with insight—I and those who follow me.
وسبحان الله وسبحان الله وما أنا من المشركين
I invite to Allah with insight—I and those who
follow me. Glory be to Allah, and I am not one of
the polytheists."
١٠٩ وما أرسلنا من قبلك إلا رجالا نوحي إليهم من أهل القرى
109. We only sent before you ˹O Prophet˺ men
inspired by Us from among the people of each
society.
أفلم يسيروا في الأرض فينظروا كيف كان عاقبة الذين من قبلهم
Have the deniers not travelled through the land to
see what was the end of those ˹destroyed˺ before
them? And surely the ˹eternal˺ Home of the Hereafter
ولدار الآخرة خير للذين اتقوا أفلا تعقلون
is far better for those mindful ˹of Allah˺. Will you
not then understand?
١١٠ حتى إذا استيأس الرسل وظنوا أنهم قد كذبوا
110. And when the messengers despaired and their
people thought the messengers had been denied help,
جاءهم نصرنا
Our help came to them ˹at last˺.
جاءهم نصرنا فنجي من نشاء
Our help came to them ˹at last˺. We then saved
whoever We willed,
ولا يرد بأسنا عن القوم المجرمين
and Our punishment is never averted from the wicked
people.
١١١ لقد كان في قصصهم عبرة لأولي الألباب
111. In their stories there is truly a lesson for
people of reason.
ما كان حديثا يفترى
This message cannot be a fabrication,
ولكن تصديق الذي بين يديه
rather ˹it is˺ a confirmation of previous
revelation,
وتفصيل كل شيء وهدى ورحمة لقوم يؤمنون
a detailed explanation of all things, a guide, and a
mercy for people of faith.